Cook, Alice, Biographical Reminiscences Audio-Visual Materials /3012av
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Alice Cook Biographical Reminiscences Audio-Visual Materials
1983-2003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cook, Alice
/3012av
5.67 cubic feet
5.7 linear ft.
Biography (genre), audiovisual materials.
Audio recordings of Alice Cook's biographical reminiscences
7587871
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, February 29, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, February 14, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Alice Hanson Cook (1903 - 1998) devoted her life to helping working people, and especially working women, on four continents. What she herself called her "patchwork career" included social work, adult education, labor organizing, a tour of foreign service at the end of World War II, twenty years teaching in Cornell's School of Industrial and Labor Relations, and authoring numerous books and articles. She was a pioneer in bringing attention to issues such as comparable worth, maternity leave, and pay equity, known for both her scholarly writings and her activism on the experiences of working women around the world.
Alice attended Northwestern University's School of Speech from 1920-1924, gaining her only formal degree. (She would later receive a number of honorary doctorates, including one from Northwestern.) While enrolled at Northwestern, Alice began her studies of both economics and social work, as well as beginning her lifelong attachment to the ideals of socialism. Early employment with the YWCA's Industrial Department in the 1920s led her to find ways to use the Y for both union support efforts and attempts to organize women workers previously ignored by unions, such as domestic servants. These early efforts with the Y led to Alice's involvement with adult labor education efforts such as the Bryn Mawr Summer School for Women Workers, Arkansas' Commonwealth College, the Southern Summer School for Workers in North Carolina, and the Hudson Shore School. They also led to her first direct employment by the union movement, as she worked for the early CIO's Textile Workers' Organizing Committee.
The 1930s and 40s also mark the beginning of Alice's interests in similar developments around the world. From 1929 to 1931, she studied in Germany under a DAAD (Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst) fellowship, beginning her long association with the German system of adult and labor education. She would return to Germany after World War II, when she became the chief of adult education in Germany's American Zone for the Education Division of the High Commission, Germany. Her travels through Germany at this time combined with her own personal experiences led her to become intrigued with questions of comparative systems of labor education. She would ultimately travel throughout both Western and Eastern Europe as well as Asia in order to carry out her research.
Alice's academic career began in 1952, when she was hired by the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in Ithaca, N.Y. She began as a researcher in the School's extension division, but moved into a full academic teaching position in 1955. She served as a well-respected teacher in the School up to her retirement in 1972.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3012: Alice Cook Papers /4118mb: ILR School Alumni Memorabilia /4238p: Alice H. Cook Memorial Celebration Photo Display /4209p: Alice H. Cook Memorial Service Photographs /4270: Francine Herman collection of Alice H. Cook Memorial Celebration files /4282: ILR School Alice Cook 100th Birthday Conference Records 5930mf: Morris L. Cooke "Industrial Management" Monograph on Microfilm
Cook, Alice Hanson
7587871
- #1 (Box 1)
  - Prof. Cook's reminiscences while at "Longhouse", no.1 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Recorded sometime from 1975-1981.
- #2 (Box 2)
  - Prof. Cook's reminiscences while at "Longhouse", no.2 (Box 2)
- #3 (Box 3)
  - Prof. Cook's reminiscences while at "Longhouse", no.3 (Box 3)
- #4 (Box 4)
  - Prof. Cook's reminiscences while at "Longhouse", no.4 (Box 4)
- #5 (Box 5)
  - Prof. Cook's reminiscences while at "Longhouse", no.5 (Box 5)
- #6 (Box 6)
  - Prof. Cook's reminiscences while at "Longhouse", no.6 (Box 6)
- #7 (Box 7)
  - Prof. Cook's reminiscences while at "Longhouse", no.7 (Box 7)
- A. Cook's 80th Birthday Party (Box 8)
  - Party for A. Cook's 80th birthday party, 1983 (Box 8)
    November 28, 1983.
- 11/4/1987 c.1 (Box 9.1)
  - 11/4/1987 (Box 9.1)
    Copy 1
- 11/4/1987 c.2 (Box 9.2)
  - 11/4/1987 (Box 9.2)
    Copy 2
- Australia:1 (11/17) (Box 10)
  1. Needham 2. Ardie 3. Working Mothers 4. Labor Department Perth
- Japan: Tape VIB (9/26) (Box 11)
  16. Hongo continued 17. Nakazawa 18. Sato 19. Watanabe 20. Yoshida and Kenbara
- Australia:3 (11/28) (Box 12)
  12. Women's Electoral Lobby continued 13. Salmon 14. Women in steel plant 15. Dept. of Labor Adelaide 16. Women's Meeting
- Australia:4 (11/29) (Box 13)
  17. Swinson Popel 18. Levi Strauss 19. Clarke's Shoes 20. Group Laundry 21. Adams
- Australia:5 (12/4) (Box 14)
  21. Adams continued 22. Trades and Labor Council 23. Employers' Association 24. Eaton 25. Committee on Sex Discrimination 26. Community Welfare
- Australia:6 (12/7) (Box 15)
  27. Further Education; Cunningham; Migrant Hostel 28. Gully 29. Lyne Browne 30. Commonwealth Dept. of Labor
- Australia:7 (12/10) (Box 16)
  30. Commonwealth Dept. of Labor 31. Nylex Corp. 32. Davenport 33. Brotherhood of St. Lawrence 34. Brickmakers Union 35. Telephone Union
- Australia:8 (12/14) (Box 17)
  35. Telephone Operators continued 36. WEL Mahlab v. Richmond 37. State Department of Labor and Industry 38. Ericson's 39. Fords 40. Rowntree 41. ACTU 42. Coleman and WEL
- Australia:9 (12/24) (Box 18)
  42. Coleman continued 43. E. Reud 44. Carl Wellesley 45. Burroughs-Welcome 46. Kearney; notes on Kunugra from Repol
- Australia:10 (12/24) (Box 19)
  49. Anthony Squires 50. Nurseries 51. ACTU Women
- Australia:11 (12/26) (Box 20)
  49. ACTU continued 50. Malley's 51. Women's Organizations 52. V. Smith 53. Fry
- Australia:12 (12/26) (Box 21)
  54. V. Read and Letter 55. Justice Evatt 56. Summary of Debriefing
- Japan:37 (Box 22)
  1. Nakanishi 2. Suzuki 3. Vocational Training
- Japan:39 (Box 23)
  4. Takeshima 5. Yamamoto 6. Kageyama
- Japan:40 (Box 24)
  7. Vocational School 8. Tada 9. Izunoi 10. Isetou
- Japan (9/21) (Box 25)
  11. Kafore 12. Ichibongase 13. Hayashi
- Japan: AC Nite VI A (9/22) (Box 26)
  13. Hayashi continued 14. Takahasi 15. Tanaka 16. Hongo
- Japan: Tape VII (Box 27)
  20. Yoshida Lab Office continued 21. Child Care Center 22. Tokyo Women's Office
- Japan: Tape AC VIII-A (Box 28)
  22. Tokyo Women's Division continued 23. Hayashi Interview 24. Hoikuen Interview 25. Hayashi continued 26. Public Officials 27. Housing Project Center
- Japan: Tape X (Box 29)
  30. Hanami 31. Kamisawa 14. Takahashi continued 32. Tax Office
- Japan: Tape XI (Box 30)
  32. Tax Office continued 32. Sato 33. Zentei 34. Seki, Nikkerei
- Japan: Tape XII (Box 31)
  34. Seki continued 35. Jichiro 36. Zenichijuro 37. Zendentsu
- Japan: Tape XIII (Box 32)
  37. Zendentsu continued 38. Yamazaki 39. Nurses Association 40. Keio Case
- Japan: XIV (Box 33)
  40. Keio Case continued 41. Akamatsu-Tanami 42. Nurses
- Japan: Tape XV (Box 34)
  42. Nurses continued 43. Kashiwabara 44. Hamawi 45. Nuita 46. Takahashi
- Japan: Tape XVI (Box 35)
  47. Nakamoto 48. Nagoya 49. Mayuma
- Japan: XVII (Box 36)
  49. Mayuma continued 50. Vocation officers 51. Ohwaki and Nagoya 52. Nagoya Meeting 53. Asano Maru
- Japan: XVIII (10/27) (Box 37)
  54. Vocational School 55. Mistsumi Co. 56. Women's Club 57. Tizuka City 58. Abe
- Japan: Tape XIX (Box 38)
  58. Abe continued 59. Ata 60. Hebe, More 61. Iwataya 62. Noguchi
- Japan: Tape XX (Box 39)
  62. Noguchi continued 63. Masuko 64. Sohyo 65. Rodo Kyokai 66. Tanaka 67. Shimazu
- Japan: Tape XXI (Box 40)
  67. Shimazu continued 68. Tomiyama and Mikake 69. Kageyama 70. Training Directors 71. ILO Association
- Unlabeled: Tape I (9/22) (Box 41)
  Vogel tapes
- Unlabeled: Tape II (Box 42)
  Vogel Tapes, Jan Ting
- Unlabeled: Tape VII (Box 43)
- Unlabeled: Tape VIIIB (Box 44)
- Unlabeled: Tape IX (Box 45)
- Unlabeled: Tape XI (Box 46)
- Unlabeled: Tape XII (Box 47)
- Unlabeled: Tape XIII (Box 48)
  Parish Notes
- Austraila:2 (11/28) (Box 49)
  5. Employers' Federation 6. Miscellaneous 7. Barney and Blanchard 8. Alan Jones 9. Bruce Buche 10. Callandar et al. 11. Latter T&LC Perth 12. Women's Electoral Lobby
- A. cook, Cassette of Broadcast - Germany: TU-General -- 25.Nov.78, 1978 (Box 50)